<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Null Hypothesis on Amit Rajan</title>
    <link>https://amitrajan012.github.io/tags/null-hypothesis/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Null Hypothesis on Amit Rajan</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 25 Nov 2018 11:36:18 +0530</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://amitrajan012.github.io/tags/null-hypothesis/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Hypothesis Testing (Part 4)</title>
      <link>https://amitrajan012.github.io/post/detailed-hypothesis-testing_4/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Nov 2018 11:36:18 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://amitrajan012.github.io/post/detailed-hypothesis-testing_4/</guid>
      <description>### Distribution-Free Tests : The one assumption for the Student&amp;rsquo;s t tests performed above was the fact that the samples should come from the normal distribution. In distribution-free tests, this restriction is relaxed, i.e. the samnples are not required to come from any specific distribution. Distribution-free tests are sometimes called as nonparametric tests. Mainly, there are two types of distribution-free tests: Wilcoxon signed-rank test(test for population mean) and Wilcoxon rank-sum test / Mann-Whitney test (analogous to the two-sample t test).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hypothesis Testing (Part 3)</title>
      <link>https://amitrajan012.github.io/post/detailed-hypothesis-testing_3/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Nov 2018 01:08:17 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://amitrajan012.github.io/post/detailed-hypothesis-testing_3/</guid>
      <description>### Tests for the Difference Between Two Means (Large-Sample) : The basic idea to conduct the hypothesis test for difference between two means is to find the distribution for the difference of two means and test whether it is equal to 0 or not. Here is an example.
Example: Suppose that a production manager for a manufacturer of industrial machinery is concerned that ball bearings produced in environments with low ambient temperatures may have smaller diameters than those produced under higher temperatures.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hypothesis Testing (Part 2)</title>
      <link>https://amitrajan012.github.io/post/detailed-hypothesis-testing_2/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Nov 2018 19:38:29 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://amitrajan012.github.io/post/detailed-hypothesis-testing_2/</guid>
      <description>### Tests for a Population Proportion : The hypothesis testing for population proportion can be conducted in a similar manner. Here are some examples to depict it.
Example: A supplier of semiconductor wafers claims that of all the wafers he supplies, no more than 10% are defective. A sample of 400 wafers is tested, and 50 of them, or 12.5%, are defective. Can we conclude that the claim is false?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hypothesis Testing (Part 1)</title>
      <link>https://amitrajan012.github.io/post/detailed-hypothesis-testing_1/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Nov 2018 09:17:41 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://amitrajan012.github.io/post/detailed-hypothesis-testing_1/</guid>
      <description>Hypothesis Testing is a method by which we can test an assumption made for a population parameter. For example, the statement $\mu &gt; 10$ is an assumption or hypothesis about the population mean $\mu$. To check the validity of this hypothesis, we must conduct a hypothesis test. Hypothesis tests are closely related to confidence intervals. Prior to performing a hypothesis test, we need to formulate the null and alternate hypothesis.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
