<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Variance on Amit Rajan</title>
    <link>https://amitrajan012.github.io/tags/variance/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Variance on Amit Rajan</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 20 Nov 2018 16:41:05 +0530</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://amitrajan012.github.io/tags/variance/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Confidence Intervals (Part 3)</title>
      <link>https://amitrajan012.github.io/post/confidence-intervals_3/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Nov 2018 16:41:05 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://amitrajan012.github.io/post/confidence-intervals_3/</guid>
      <description>#### Confidence Intervals with Paired Data : Sometimes an experiment is designed in such a way that each item in one sample is paired with an item in the other. Let $D_1, D-2, &amp;hellip;, D_n$ be a small random sample $(n \leq 30)$ of differences of the paired data. If the population of differences is approximately normal, the $100(1 - \alpha) %$ confidence interval for the mean difference $\mu_D$ is given as:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Random Variables (Part 2: Continuous Random Variables)</title>
      <link>https://amitrajan012.github.io/post/randomvariables_part2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Nov 2018 03:01:07 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://amitrajan012.github.io/post/randomvariables_part2/</guid>
      <description>#### Continuous Random Variables : A continuous random variable is a random variable which can take infinitely many values. The probabilities associated with a continuous RV is defined by probability density function(PDF).
 #### Probability Density Function (PDF) : As a continuous RV takes infinite values, the probability $P(X=x)$ for it can not be defined and takes a value of 0. Instead we define a probability density funaction, which intutively depicts probability per unit space, where space is defined by the range of the underlying random variable.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Random Variables (Part 1: Discrete Random Variables)</title>
      <link>https://amitrajan012.github.io/post/random-variables/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Nov 2018 13:11:27 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://amitrajan012.github.io/post/random-variables/</guid>
      <description>Random Variable is a variable whose possible values are numerical outcomes of a random phenomenon or experiment. In other words, a random variable assigns a numeric value to each outcome of a random experiment. For example, if we roll a fair die, the random variable $X$ describing the experiment will take the values $1,2,3,4,5,6$ (which are the possible outcomes of the experiment). There are two types of random variables: discrete and continuous.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Think Stats: Chapter 2</title>
      <link>https://amitrajan012.github.io/post/chapter-2-descriptive-statistics/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Aug 2018 04:17:12 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://amitrajan012.github.io/post/chapter-2-descriptive-statistics/</guid>
      <description>2.1 Means and averages Mean of a sample is a summary statistics that can be computed as (where n is the total number of samples): $$\mu = \frac{1}{n} \sum_i{x_i}$$ An average is one of many summary statistics that can be used to describe the typical value or the central tendency of a sample.
2.2 Variance As mean describes the central tendency of a sample, Variance is intended to describe the spread.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
